[
    {
        "question": "Ic (<em>habban</em>) #### ðe to secgenne sum þing⁠ — I have something to say",
        "correctAnswer": "hæbbe",
        "explanation": "Here 'habban' is in the first person singular form '<em>hæbbe</em>' because the subject is 'I'",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "habbe",
                "explanation": "When conjugated in the singular or past, the 'a' in 'habban' becomes an 'æ'"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðu (<em>libban</em>) #### be godra manna ælmessan⁠ — You live by alms of good men",
        "correctAnswer": "leofast",
        "explanation": "Here 'libban' is in the second person singular form '<em>leofast</em>' because the subject is 'You",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Swa (<em>secgan</em>) #### ðæs huses hlaford⁠ — The lord of this house says so",
        "correctAnswer": "secgað|secgaþ",
        "explanation": "Here 'secgan' is in the third person singular form '<em>secgað</em>' because the subject is 'the lord'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>hycgan</em>) #### his ealle hu ge hie beswicen⁠ — All think of this, how you may deceive them",
        "correctAnswer": "hycgaþ|hycgað;",
        "explanation": "Here 'hycgan' is in the plural form '<em>hycgað</em>' because the subject is 'all'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðis leoht we (<em>habban</em>) #### wið nytenu gemæne⁠ — This light we have in common with beasts",
        "correctAnswer": "habbaþ|habbað",
        "explanation": "Here 'habban' is in the plural form '<em>habbað</em>' because the subject is 'We'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hie be urum larum (<em>libban</em>) ####⁠ — They live according to our instructions",
        "correctAnswer": "libbaþ|libbað",
        "explanation": "Here 'libban' is in the plural form '<em>libbað</em>' because the subject is 'They'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic ðe orlæg (<em>secgan</em>) ####⁠ — I told thee thy fate",
        "correctAnswer": "secgde ",
        "explanation": "Here 'secgan' is in the first person singular form '<em>secgde</em>' because the subject is 'I",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðu (<em>hycgan</em>) #### on ellen ac wærwyrde sceal wisfæst hæle breostum hycgan⁠ — You thought on valour, but a wise and cautious man holds his thoughts to his breast",
        "correctAnswer": "hogdest",
        "explanation": "Here 'hycgan' is in the second person singular past form '<em>hogdest</em>' because the subject is 'You'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Her (<em>habban</em>) #### se cyning his hired æt Gleaweceastre⁠ — On this year, the king had his court at Gloucester",
        "correctAnswer": "hæfde",
        "explanation": "Here 'habban' is in the third person singular past form '<em>hæfde</em>' because the subject is 'the king'",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "hafde",
                "explanation": "Close, but remember, 'habban' takes an 'æ' instead of an 'a' in all past tense conjugations"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "We ealne ðysne gear (<em>libban</em>) #### mid ures lichoman willan⁠ — we have lived all this year as it was pleasing to our body",
        "correctAnswer": "lifdon",
        "explanation": "Here 'libban' is in the plural form '<em>lifdon</em>' because the subject is 'We'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ge guilty synne (<em>secgan</em>) ####⁠ — You the guilty spoke sin",
        "correctAnswer": "sægdon",
        "explanation": "Here 'secgan' is in the plural past form '<em>sægdon</em>' because the subject is the plural 'You'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hie (<em>hycgan</em>) #### inwit and facen on heortan geþoncum⁠ — They thought deceit and treachery with the thoughts of their heart",
        "correctAnswer": "hogdon",
        "explanation": "Here 'hycgan' is in the third person singular past form '<em>hogdon</em>' because the subject is 'They'",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "",
                "explanation": ""
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic bi me (<em>secgan</em>) #### ðis sarspell⁠ — I tell this lament about myself",
        "correctAnswer": "secge",
        "explanation": "Here 'secgan' is in the first person singular form '<em>secge</em>' because the subject is 'I'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Æðelwulf his dohtor (<em>habban</em>) #### him to cuene⁠ — Ethelwulf had his daughter for his queen",
        "correctAnswer": "hæfde",
        "explanation": "Here 'habban' is in the third person singular form '<em>hæfde</em>' because the subject is 'Ethelwulf'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hie (<em>habban</em>) #### hine mid heom oþ ðet hie ofslogon hine⁠ — They had him with them until they slew him",
        "correctAnswer": "hæfdon",
        "explanation": "Here 'habban' is in the plural form '<em>hæfdon</em>' because the subject is 'They'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "For ðam ic lybbe and ge (<em>libban</em>) ####⁠ — Because I live, you live",
        "correctAnswer": "libbaþ|libbað",
        "explanation": "Here 'libban' is in the plural form '<em>libbað</em>' because the subject is the plural 'You'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Wynnum ond þeawum ic (<em>libban</em>) ####⁠ — I lived joyously and virutously",
        "correctAnswer": "lifde",
        "explanation": "Here 'libban' is in the first person past singular form '<em>lifde</em>' because the subject is 'I'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Heo (<em>hycgan</em>) #### georne ðæt hire mægþhad clæne geheolde⁠ — She earnestly intended to keep her maidenhood pure",
        "correctAnswer": "hogde",
        "explanation": "Here 'hycgan' is in the third person singular past form '<em>hogde</em>' because the subject is 'She'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ge (<em>habban</em>) #### us gedon laðe Pharaone⁠ — You have made us hateful to Pharoh",
        "correctAnswer": "habbaþ|habbað",
        "explanation": "Here 'habban' is in the plural form '<em>habbað</em>' because the subject is the plural 'You",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðu me forlæred (<em>habban</em>) ####⁠ — You have seduced me",
        "correctAnswer": "hæfst",
        "explanation": "Here 'habban' is in the third person singular form '<em>hæfst</em>' because the subject is 'You'",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "hæbbast|habbast|habast|hæbast|habst|hæbst",
                "explanation": "Remember, the 'b' in 'habban' becomes an 'f' in the 2nd and 3rd singular present, and all past tense conjugations"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "He cwæþ to him ðu wast ðæt ic ðe (<em>lufian</em>) ####⁠ — He said to him 'you know that I love you'",
        "correctAnswer": "lufie",
        "explanation": "Here 'lufian' is in the first person singular form '<em>lufie</em>' because the subject is 'I'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Eala ðu scippend heofones and eorþan! Ðu ðe on ðam ecan setle (<em>ricsian</em>) ####!⁠ — Oh you the creator of heaven and earth! You who reigns on the eternal seat!",
        "correctAnswer": "ricsast",
        "explanation": "Here 'ricsian' is in the second person singular form '<em>ricsast</em>' because the subject is 'You",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He (<em>gaderian</em>) #### sum gehwæde andgyt of ðære bec⁠ — He gathered some little information from the book",
        "correctAnswer": "gaderað|gaderaþ",
        "explanation": "Here 'gaderian' is in the third person singular form '<em>gaderað</em>' because the subject is 'He'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He het ond we (<em>andswarian</em>) ####⁠ — He calls and we answer",
        "correctAnswer": "andswariaþ|andswariað;",
        "explanation": "Here 'andswarian' is in the first person plural form '<em>andswariað</em>' as the subject is 'We'",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "andswaraþ",
                "explanation": "'Andswaraþ' is the third person form. Here 'he' is linked to the verb 'het'. 'Andswarian'should by in the plural form '<em>andswariað</em>' as its subject is 'We'."
            } 
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Heofonas (<em>bodian</em>) #### oððe cýðaþ wuldor Godes⁠ — The heavens procalimed the glory of God",
        "correctAnswer": "bodiaþ|bodiað",
        "explanation": "Here 'bodian' is in the third person plural form '<em>bodiað</em>' as the subject is plural: 'the heavens'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hie (<em>hatian</em>) #### hiera hieramonna unþeawas⁠ — They hate the vices of their subjects",
        "correctAnswer": "hatiaþ|hatiað",
        "explanation": "Here 'hatian' is in the first person singular past form '<em>hatiað</em>' because the subject is 'I'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic (<em>timbrian</em>) #### setl ðin⁠ — I built your seat",
        "correctAnswer": "timbrode ",
        "explanation": "Here 'timbrian' is in the first person singular past form '<em>timbrode</em>' because the subject is 'I",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "timbrie",
                "explanation": "'Timbrie' is the present singular form. Here 'timbrian' should be the past tense first person singular form '<em>timbrode</em>'"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "He eallum mannum (<em>lufian</em>) ####⁠ — He loved all men",
        "correctAnswer": "lufode",
        "explanation": "Here 'lufian' is in the third person singular past form '<em>lufode</em>' because the subject is 'he'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðes apostol Iacobus (<em>bodian</em>) #### on Iudea lande⁠ — This apostle, Jacob, preached in the land of Judea",
        "correctAnswer": "bodode",
        "explanation": "Here 'bodian' is in the third person singular past form '<em>bodode</em>' because the subject is 'Jacob'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hie (<em>timbrian</em>) #### langscipu mid æscum⁠ — They built the longships with ash trees",
        "correctAnswer": "timbredon",
        "explanation": "Here 'timbrian' is in the third person plural form '<em>timbredon</em>' because the subject is 'They'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "On ðam dagum (<em>ricsian</em>) #### Æþelbyrht cyning ond his wif on Cantwarebyrig⁠ — On this day, Ethelbyrt and his wife reigned in Canterbury",
        "correctAnswer": "ricsodon",
        "explanation": "Here 'ricsian' is in the third person plural past form '<em>ricsodon</em>' because the subject is 'Ethelbert and his wife'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Him englas (<em>andswarian</em>) ####⁠ — The angels answered him",
        "correctAnswer": "andswaredon",
        "explanation": "Here 'andswarian' is in the third person singular past form '<em>andswaredon</em>' because the subject is 'The angels'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic (<em>gaderian</em>) #### ðyder eall ðæt me gewexen is⁠ — I gather thither all that is grown by me",
        "correctAnswer": "gaderie",
        "explanation": "Here 'gaderian' is in the first person singular form '<em>gaderie</em>' because the subject is 'I'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hwy (<em>bodian</em>) #### þu mine rihtwisnesse mid þinne fulan muð⁠ — Why do you proclaim my justice with your foul mouth?",
        "correctAnswer": "bodast",
        "explanation": "Here 'bodian' is in the first person singular form '<em>bodast</em>' because the subject is 'you'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ne mæg middaneard eow hatian ac he (<em>hatian</em>) #### me⁠ — The world may not hate you, but he hates me",
        "correctAnswer": "hataþ|hatað",
        "explanation": "Here 'hatian' is in the third person singular form '<em>hataþ</em>' because the subject is 'he'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hie (<em>lufian</em>) #### mid lacum ða ðe læs agun⁠ — They show love with offerings to they who possess less",
        "correctAnswer": "lufiaþ|lufiað",
        "explanation": "Here 'lufian' is in the third person plural form '<em>lufiaþ</em>' because the subject is 'they'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ge (<em>andswarian</em>) #### to þone cyning⁠ — You answer to the king",
        "correctAnswer": "andswariaþ|andswariað",
        "explanation": "Here 'andswarian' is in the plural form '<em>andswariaþ</em>' because the subject is the plural 'you'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "We (<em>timbrian</em>) #### þisne ceastra⁠ — We built this city",
        "correctAnswer": "timbriaþ|timbriað",
        "explanation": "Here 'timbrian' is in the plural form '<em>timbriaþ</em>' because the subject is 'we'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic (<em>timbrian</em>) #### min hus on ðæm beorgum⁠ — I built my house in the mountains",
        "correctAnswer": "timbrode",
        "explanation": "Here 'timbrian' is in the first person singular past form '<em>timbrode</em>' because the subject is 'I'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Swa he (<em>ricsian</em>) #### and wið rihte wan ana wið eallum⁠ — So he ruled and challenged justice, one against all ",
        "correctAnswer": "ricsode",
        "explanation": "Here 'ricsian' is in the third person singular form '<em>ricsode</em>' because the subject is 'he'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "ðæm ðe ær (<em>hatian</em>) #### eow⁠ — those that formerly hated you",
        "correctAnswer": "hatedon",
        "explanation": "Here 'hatian' is in the third person singular form '<em>hatedon</em>' because the subject is the demonstrative pronoun 'those'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðæt folc (<em>gaderian</em>) #### mid micle menio ðæra fugela⁠ — The people gathered a great number of the birds",
        "correctAnswer": "gaderode",
        "explanation": "Here 'gaderian' is in the third person plural form '<em>gaderode</em>' because the subject is 'the folk'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hie hine (<em>lufian</em>) #### lease muðe⁠ — They loved him falsely with their mouth",
        "correctAnswer": "lufodon",
        "explanation": "Here 'lufian' is in the third person singular form '<em>lufodon</em>' because the subject is 'they'",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ymb Bethleem (<em>bodian</em>) #### englas ðæt acenned wæs Crist on eorþan⁠ — Angels announced throughout Bethlehem that Christ was born on earth",
        "correctAnswer": "bododon",
        "explanation": "Here 'bodian' is in the third person plural past form '<em>bododon</em>' because the subject is 'angels'",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "bodiaþ",
                "explanation": "'Bodiaþ' is the present form. Here 'bodian' should be the past tense plural form '<em>bododon</em>'"
            }
        ]
    },
        {
            "question": "Ic (<em>fremman</em>) #### gu&thorn;e⁠ — I make war",
            "correctAnswer": "fremme",
            "explanation": "Here 'fremman' is in the first person singular form '<em>fremme</em>' because the subject is 'I'",
            "commonMistakes": []
        },
        {
            "question": "&THORN;u (<em>nerian</em>) #### &thorn;a cildras⁠ — You save the children",
            "correctAnswer": "nerest",
            "explanation": "Here 'nerian' is in the second person singular form '<em>nerest</em>' because the subject is 'You",
            "commonMistakes": [
                {
                    "incorrectAnswer": "neriest",
                    "explanation": "Remember, the second person singular form of 'nerian' is '<em>nerest</em>' because 'nerian' drops its 'i' in some conjugations"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "question": "He minum l&aelig;rum (<em>hieran</em>) ####⁠ — He listens to my teachings",
            "correctAnswer": "hierð|hierþ",
            "explanation": "Here 'hieran' is in the third person singular form '<em>hierð</em>' because the subject is 'He'",
            "commonMistakes": [
                {
                    "incorrectAnswer": "hiereð|hiereþ",
                    "explanation": "Remember, 'hieran' drops the 'e' before a dental fricative"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "question": "We (<em>l&aelig;ran</em>) #### eald Englisc on &thorn;&aelig;m minstere⁠ — We teach Old English in the monastery",
            "correctAnswer": "l&aelig;ra&thorn;",
            "explanation": "Here 'l&aelig;ran' is in the first person plural form '<em>l&aelig;ra&thorn;</em>' as the subject is 'We'",
            "commonMistakes": []
        },
        {
            "question": "Hie hergia&thorn; and to scipe (<em>l&aelig;dan</em>) ####⁠ — they harry and carry off the plunder to their ships",
            "correctAnswer": "lædaþ|lædað",
            "explanation": "Here 'l&aelig;dan' is in the third person plural form '<em>lædað</em>' as the subject is 'They'",
            "commonMistakes": []
        },
        {
            "question": "Ic (<em>sendan</em>) #### &aelig;rendracan to minum hlaforde⁠ — I sent a messenger to my lord",
            "correctAnswer": "sende",
            "explanation": "Here 'sendan' is in the first person singular past form '<em>sende</em>' because the subject is 'I'",
            "commonMistakes": [
                {
                    "incorrectAnswer": "sendde",
                    "explanation": "Remember, when a double d is proceeded by a consonant, the double is reduced to single so the correct form is 'sende'"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "question": "Morgensteorran &eth;e we o&eth;re naman &aelig;fensteorra nemnan (<em>hieran</em>) ####⁠ — The morning star which we hear called evening star by another name",
            "correctAnswer": "hierdest",
            "explanation": "Here 'hieran' is in the first person plural past form '<em>hierdest</em>' because the subject is 'We",
            "commonMistakes": []
        },
        {
            "question": "Hie halig God (<em>nerian</em>) ####⁠ — They are saved by holy God",
            "correctAnswer": "neredon",
            "explanation": "Here 'nerian' is in the third person plural past form '<em>neredon</em>' because the subject is 'They'",
            "commonMistakes": [
                {
                    "incorrectAnswer": "neriedon",
                    "explanation": "Remember, the third person plural past form of 'nerian' is '<em>neredon</em>' because it drops its 'i' in some conjugations"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "question": "We (<em>fremman</em>) #### swa and Frean hyrde⁠ — We did so and obeyed the lord",
            "correctAnswer": "fremedon",
            "explanation": "Here 'fremman' is in the first person plural past form '<em>fremedon</em>' because the subject is 'We'",
            "commonMistakes": []
        },
        {
            "question": "Hie (<em>feran</em>) #### ofer s&aelig;⁠ — They go overseas",
            "correctAnswer": "ferað|feraþ",
            "explanation": "Here 'feran' is in the third person plural form '<em>ferað</em>' because the subject is 'They'",
            "commonMistakes": []
        },
        {
            "question": "Hie (<em>feran</em>) #### to Rome⁠ — They went to Rome",
            "correctAnswer": "ferdon",
            "explanation": "Here 'feran' is in the third person plural past form '<em>ferdon</em>' because the subject is 'They'",
            "commonMistakes": []
        },
        {
            "question": "&THORN;a (<em>sendan</em>) #### se cyning to &thorn;am flotan Leofsig ealdorman — Then the king sent Alderman Leofsig to the fleet",
            "correctAnswer": "sende",
            "explanation": "Here 'sendan' is in the third person singular past form '<em>sende</em>' because the subject is 'The King'",
            "commonMistakes": [
                {
                    "incorrectAnswer": "sendest",
                    "explanation": "Here 'sendan' should be the third person singular past form '<em>sende</em>' because the subject is 'The King'. While &thorn;a resembles the second person <em>'&thorn;u'</em>, it actually means 'then'"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "question": "Wyrd oft (<em>nerian</em>) #### unfægne eorl &thorn;onne his ellen deah⁠ — Fate often saves a man not fated to die",
            "correctAnswer": "nereð|nereþ",
            "explanation": "Here 'nerian' is in the third person singular form '<em>nereð</em>' because the subject is 'Wyrd'",
            "commonMistakes": [
                {
                    "incorrectAnswer": "nerieð|nerieþ",
                    "explanation": "Remember, the third person singular form of 'nerian' is '<em>nereð</em>' because it drops its 'i' in some conjugations"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "question": "Ic (<em>hieran</em>) #### &thorn;u⁠ — I hear you",
            "correctAnswer": "hiere",
            "explanation": "Here 'hieran' is in the first person singular form '<em>hiere</em>' because the subject is 'I'",
            "commonMistakes": []
        },
        {
            "question": "Ic (<em>l&aelig;dan</em>) #### &thorn;one micel here⁠ — I led the great army",
            "correctAnswer": "lædde",
            "explanation": "Here 'l&aelig;dan' is in the first person singular past form '<em>lædde</em>' because the subject is 'I'",
            "commonMistakes": [
                {
                    "incorrectAnswer": "læde",
                    "explanation": "Unlike 'sendan', Lædan does not drop double 'd's' because they are proceeded by a vowel. So, here 'l&aelig;dan' is in the first person singular past form '<em>lædde</em>' because the subject is 'I'"
                }
            ]
        },
        {
            "question": "Ic (<em>l&aelig;ran</em>) #### leden and grecisc⁠ — I taught Latin and Greek",
            "correctAnswer": "lærde",
            "explanation": "Here 'l&aelig;ran' is in the first person singular past form '<em>lærde</em>' because the subject is 'I'",
            "commonMistakes": [
                {
                    "incorrectAnswer": "lærede",
                    "explanation": "While <em>l&aelig;ran</em> takes an 'e' in the present first person singular, here 'l&aelig;ran' is in the past tense first person singular form '<em>lædde</em>' because the subject is 'I'"
                }
            ]
        }
    ]    
